Guide to the Edward K. Barsky Papers ALBA.125
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward K. Barsky Papers
1936-1970
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975
ALBA.125
2.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
Edward K. Barsky (1897-1975) was a prominent physician who led a group of American medical volunteers in Spain during the Civil War. After the war, he served as Chairman of the Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee (JAFRC), an organization dedicated to aiding Spanish refugees and lobbying the U.S. leadership on behalf of the deposed Republican government. Barsky and the entire board of JAFRC were charged with contempt of Congress and convicted in June 1947 for refusing to turn over the group’s records. Barsky was sentenced to six months in prison. Following his release the New York Board of Regents moved to suspend his medical license, a decision that was upheld by the Supreme Court in 1954. These papers reflect Barsky’s humanitarian work on behalf of Spain and document the court cases that stemmed from these progressive activities.
Provenance
The The Edward K. Barsky Papers were donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Vita Barsky in the late 1970s. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward K. Barsky was born in New York on June 6, 1895, the son of Dr. Joseph Barsky, a promiment New York physician and a founder of Beth Israel Hospital. One of a family of six children, he attended public elementary school, graduated from Townsend Harris High School and received his college degree from City College of New York. Following the example of his father and two of his brothers, Barsky pursued a career in medicine receiving his formal education at Columbia University of Physicians and Surgeons and subsequently conducting post-graduate study abroad in Vienna, Berlin, and Paris. Beginning in 1919 he served a two-year internship at Beth Israel Hospital where he subsequently advanced through the positions of Visiting Staff, Assistant Adjunct Surgeon, and Adjunct Surgeon before assuming the position of Associate Surgeon in 1934. In November 1935, Barsky became a member of the Communist Party.
With the outbreak civil war in Spain in 1936, Barsky joined with a group of concerned New York physicians to establish the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) -- an adjunct organization to the North America Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy, later known as the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy. The AMB arranged for the shipment of ambulances and other medical equipment and supplies, and in January 1937 sent a fully outfitted medical team of doctors, nurses, and technicians to Spain with Barsky at the helm. Additional medical personnel soon followed and under Barsky's command, base hospitals and convalescent homes were set up in schools and monasteries. Emergency units were established on the front lines in ambulances, makeshift tents, and a mobile medical hospital outfitted with a battery-powered operating room. By the following year 117 American doctors, nurses, and ambulance drivers had volunteered to serve in Spain. Barsky returned briefly to the United States in 1937 to conduct a national speaking tour, securing additional funds and supplies for the AMB. With his returned to Spain, he assumed charge of the Sanitary Services of the International Brigade, overseeing hundreds of international medical volunteers -- a position he held until the withdrawal of the foreign forces in January 1939.
Back in the United States Barsky resumed his work at Beth Israel Hospital. He married Vita Lauter, a graduate of the University of Wisconsin, and the couple had one child -- a daughter named Angela. In the wake of the war in Spain, Barsky turned his attention to securing relief for Spanish exiles who were living in deplorable conditions in French refugee camps, and Republican prisoners in Spain. In 1941 Barsky played a key role in the formation of the Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee (JAFRC), an organization dedicated to aiding Spanish refugees and lobbying the U.S. leadership on behalf of the deposed Republican government. With Barsky as chairman, the organization raised closed to $400,000 in its first two years of operation. By 1945, however, the JAFRC's progressive agenda attracted the hostile attention of the House on Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). Barksy, Executive Secretary Helen R. Bryan, and Executive Board members of JAFRC were subpoenaed to appear before the committee, surrender financial records, and turn over the names of contributors and recipients of aid. After refusing to comply with HUAC demands, Barsky and entire board of JAFRC were charged with contempt of Congress and convicted in June 1947.
Three years of appeals that challenged the constitutionality of the HUAC hearings ended in 1950 when the Supreme Court refused to review the convictions. The board members, including novelist Howard Fast, were sentenced to three months in prison, and Barsky, as the JAFRC's chairman, was sentenced to six months in the Federal Penitentiary in Petersburg, Virginia and fined $500. Following his release, the New York State Board of Regents moved to censure Barsky and -- citing his conviction and subsequent imprisonment -- suspended his medical license. Although he received the unstinting support of his medical colleagues who filed an Amici Curiae on his behalf, in 1954, after four years of appeals, the Supreme Court upheld a six-month suspension of his license. Writing in a dissenting opinion, Judge William O. Douglas asserted, "When a doctor cannot save lives in America because he is opposed to Franco in Spain, it is time to call a halt and look critically at the neurosis that has possessed us."
Barsky remained committed to progressive causes throughout his life. In 1952 he worked on behalf of the American Labor Party and its candidate, Vincent Hallihan, who was chief counsel for Harry Bridges and at the time of the election was serving a six months sentence for contempt of congress. During the 1960s, Barsky was active with the Medical Committee for Human Rights, which provided emergency medical services for civil rights and peace movement workers in the South. He was also affiliated with the New York labor movement, working for many years as a security plan panel physician for District Council 65. In 1967, the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade marked their 30th anniversary with a tribute honoring Barsky's achievements on behalf the Spanish Republic. Barsky continued his professional relationship with Beth Israel Hospital throughout the remainder of his life, serving as consulting surgeon in his later years. On February 11, 1975, Edward Barsky died at the age of 78.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Aid to Spain, 1937-1957, documents Barsky's work in Spain and his subsequent efforts on behalf of the Spanish refugees who were force into exile after the fall of the Republic. Materials that date from the Spanish Civil War include medical reports issued by the International Brigades; commendations from the Spanish Republic; clippings pertaining to Barsky's activities in Spain; AMB pamphlets; and a license granting Barsky permission to use a camera.
The bulk of these materials cover Barsky's work with the JAFRC, from its inception in 1941 to its dissolution in 1955. Included here is correspondence, reports, press releases, pamphlets, newsletters, materials related to fundraising events, the organization's constitution, and copies of addresses delivered by Barsky in his capacity as chairman. Notable materials include records and correspondence dealing with HUAC's investigation of the organization; and signed letters from Sean O'Casey, Dorothy Parker, and Paul Robeson promoting the cause of the JAFRC.
Also notable is the text of a Henry Wallace speech decrying the U.S. government's pro-Franco policy; pamphlets, articles, and correspondence relating to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) including materials protesting VALB's inclusion on the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations; a transcript of a meeting between Milton Wolff and the U.S. State Department on Spanish prisoners condemned to death; and clippings related to the Spanish refugee crisis.
Series II, Subject Files, 1950-1973. These files offer a glimpse into some of Barsky's political and professional preoccupations. Included here are materials related to his activities with the America Labor Party; a speech Barsky delivered paying tribute to editor of the Soviet Russia Today (later named New World Review) and Communist Party organizer Jessica Smith; and a proposal for the establishment of a private hospital in New York City.
Series III Trials & Hearings, 1946-1960, consist of legal records pertaining to the JAFRC's contempt trials, the Board of Regent's action against Barsky's, and the court cases that ensued. In addition to briefs and legal proceedings, are copies of an Amici Curiae brief -- filed by Barsky's medical colleagues --, and a petition of support signed by 621 physicians. This series also contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, with letters of support written to Barsky while he was imprisoned, and character references written to the parole board on his behalf prior to his release. There is also a separate file of correspondence related to the Board of Regents hearings and trials. Notable is a signed letter from journalist Vincent Sheean offering a first-hand account of Barsky's work in Spain and a review of Sheean efforts to defend Barsky and other members of the JAFRC during their contempt trials. There are also several documents that record his incarceration including a receipt of property noting the garments and other personal effects he surrendered when he entered the federal penitentiary to serve his term.
Series IV, Writings, Undated, 1937-1958, includes Barsky's unpublished memoir, "A Surgeon Goes to War," which gives an account of his time organizing medical units and operating on the frontlines in Spain; and a signed typescript of Sandor Voros' work on the American hospitals and international medical services during the Spanish Civil War. This series also includes a copy of Bulgarian physician Tsvetan Angelov Kristanov's account of his term as medical director of the International Brigades in Spain. The book, which is in Russian, includes a personal inscription to Barsky from the author, and a partial translation of the introduction. There is also an essay by an unidentified physician (perhaps Barsky) describing setting up emergency surgery units at the front. Two essays without attribution on academic freedom and co-education may be the work of Vita Lauter Barsky.
Arrangement
Series I and II are arranged alphabetically. Series III consists of two sections: the legal proceedings are arranged chronologically, followed by subject files, which are arranged alphabetically. Series IV is arranged alphabetically by author.
Organized into three series:
Missing Title
I. Aid to Spain, 1937-1957.
II. Subject Files, 1950-1973.
III. Trials & Hearings, 1946-1960.
IV. Writings, Undated, 1937-1958.
Related Material
Fredericka Martin Papers, ALBA #1
Frances Patai Papers, ALBA #131
Mildred Rackley Papers, ALBA #97
Tamiment Verticle File: OF - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee
Other Institutions:
Sandor Voros Spanish Civil War Collection. Adelphi University Library.
Spanish Refugee Relief Association Records. Columbia University, Rare Book, Manuscript Library.
American Friends of Spanish Democracy Records. Manuscript & Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Separated Material
Photographs were separated from Barsky’s manuscript materials in the course of processing. For further information related to the scope and contents of his photograph collection see, The Guide to the Edward K. Barsky Photograph Collection.
Articles.; Briefs (legal documents); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Foreign public opinion.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Medical care.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Drafts (documents); Correspondence.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Legal documents.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Kristanov, Tsvetan Angelov.; Medical Committee for Human Rights (U.S.).; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy.; O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Parker, Dorothy, 1893-1967.; Smith, Jessica, 1895-1983; Sheean, Vincent, 1899-1975; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion.; Voros, Sandor.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965; Wolff, Milton.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975; Barsky, Vita; Beth Israel Medical Center (New York, N.Y.).; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976
- Series I: Relief to Spain, 1937-1951
  - Advisory Committee on Voluntary Foreign Aid, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Committee for Spanish Freedom, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appeal for Amnesty (Organization to Aid Spain’s Political Prisoners), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barsky, Edward: Address on Foreign Relations with Spain (Free Speech Forum of the Newspaper Guild), Jan 23, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - French Public Health and Relief Organizations, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Friends of the Spanish Republic: Memorandum Submitted to the United Nations Conference, Apr 25, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Brigades: 25th Anniversary, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Committee of Coordination and Information to Aid Republican Spain, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee (JAFRC): Address by Barsky (Hotel Diplomat): Clipping, Nov 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky at Mexico City Convention, Aug 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky, [1945?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky, Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky (Madison Square Garden), Sep 24, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - JAFRC: Address by Barsky: Commemoration of the founding of Spain, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - JAFRC: "Campaign Bulletin", 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - JAFRC: Convention of Solidarity (Mexico City), Aug 1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - JAFRC: Constitution, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - JAFRC: Correspondence, undated, 1942-1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - JAFRC: Correspondence: O’Casey, Sean, Feb 3, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - JAFRC: Correspondence: Parker, Dorothy, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - JAFRC: Correspondence: Robeson, Paul, Sep 28, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - JAFRC: Correspondence: Welles, Sumner, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - JAFRC: Financial Records, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - JAFRC: "Free Spain": Bulletin, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - JAFRC: Fundraising Tribute: Jo Davidson, [May 1948?] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - JAFRC: Fundraising Tributes & Events, 1943-1945, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - JAFRC: House Un-American Activities Committee, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - JAFRC: House Un-American Activities Committee: Congressional Record, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - JAFRC: International Revenue Investigation: Barsky Interview (Transcript) & Correspondence, 1947, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - JAFRC: Organizational History, May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - JAFRC: Press Releases, Pamphlets & Leaflets, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - JAFRC: Reports, undated, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - JAFRC: Resolutions, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - JAFRC: Spanish Refugee Appeal: Inaugural Dinner (Lillian Hellman, guest of honor), Mar 22, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - JAFRC: Spanish Refugee Appeal: Pamphlets & Programs, undated, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - JAFRC: Truman, Harry S.: Letters of Appeal, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - JAFRC: Unitarian Service Committee Report in The Christian Register, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy: Herman Reissing Testimony before Dies Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy: Pamphlets, circa 1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Spain: Anti-Franco Addresses: Phillip Jordan, Fred Myers, Quentin Reynolds, undated, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Spain: Anti-Franco Address: Juan Negrin, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Spain: Anti-Franco Address: Henry Wallace, Apr 4, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Spain: Refugees, Aid & Politics: Clippings, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Spanish Civil War: Barsky, Edward: Clippings, 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Spanish Civil War: Barsky, Edward: Commendations Issued by Spanish Republic, Jun 1938 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Civil War: Barsky, Edward: Photographic License (Issued in Barcelona, Spain), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Civil War: International Brigades: Medical Reports & Statistics, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Civil War: "Lift the Embargo" Rally, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civil War: Ministry of National Defence Reports, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civil War: Public Health Reports & Pamphlets, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civil War: Socorro Rojo: Pamphlet, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Currency, 1931, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Prisoners: Milton Wolff: Report on State Department Meeting, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - United Nations: Relations with Spain, undated, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1950-1973
  - American Labor Party Election: Speech & Certificate of Election, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Civil Defense Pamphlet (French), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - China Welfare Appeal, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Continental Hospital: Outline for the Establishment of a Private Hospital, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Personal, undated, 1956-1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Douglas, Justice William O.: Address & Opinion, 1947, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Medical Committee for Human Rights, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - National Conference for New Politics, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Segal, Ben: Eulogy delivered by Edward Barsky, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Smith, Jessica: Tribute Address by Barsky, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Un-American Activities Committee: Protest Literature, 1947, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - World Council of Peace, Jun 1951 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Series III: Trials & Hearings, 1947-1960
  - Barsky, et al. v. United States of America: US Court of Appeals: Joint Appendix to Briefs, Vol. I, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Barsky, et al. v. United States of America: US Court of Appeals: Joint Appendix to Briefs, Vol. II, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Barsky, et al. v. United States of America: Petition for Rehearing, Oct 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Barsky, et al. v. United States of America: US Court of Appeals: Brief for Appellants, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - United States of America v. Barsky, et al.: Indictment & Brief on Motion to Dismiss, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee v. United States of America: US Court of Appeals, Feb 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee v. United States of America: Writ or Certiorari to US Court of Appeals, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee v. United States of America: Brief for Petitioner, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New York State Department of Education, Committee on Grievances: Hearing Transcript, Feb 1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York State Department of Education, Committee on Grievances: Revocation of Barsky’s License, Apr 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - New York State Department of Education: Report of the Regents’ Committee on Discipline, Jul 1951 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Barsky v. Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York (NY Supreme Court): Petition to Review & Briefs, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Barsky v. Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York: Amici Curiae Brief, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Barsky v. Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York (US Supreme Court): Brief, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Barsky v. Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York (US Supreme Court): Opinion & Dissent, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - New York State Department of Education, Board of Regents: Petition of Support, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - NYS Department of Education, Board of Regents: Barsky’s Appeal for Reinstatement, Jul 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - NYS Department of Education, Board of Regents: Suspension of Practice, Jun 1954-Oct 1954 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - NYS Department of Education, Board of Regents: Termination of Suspension, Oct 1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Workmen’s Compensation Board Hearing, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Philip Reisman v. Jack Froman et al. (Malpractice Case), 1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Character References: Notes on Solicited Individuals, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: Trials, 1946-1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1947-1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: NYS Department of Education, Board of Regents, 1950-1951, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Prison Records: Statement of Sentence; Receipt of Personal Property, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Writings
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Forward and Chapter 1 (unpublished memoir), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 4, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 5, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 6, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 7, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 8, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 9, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 11, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 12, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 13, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 14, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 15, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 16, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 17, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Chapter 18, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Barsky, Edward: "Surgeon Goes to War," Photocopy of Entire Manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)